it's often said that a spinner is like
the square root of a vector and I'll say
that's kind of true but slightly
inaccurate
if you're thinking of taking an actual
square root of a vector and getting a
spinner that's not correct what is true
is that we can take a 3D vector and cut
up the vector into two pieces called
poly spinners
so it's better to say that a 3D Vector
can be factored into a column spinner
and a row spinner
we're continuing with our introduction
to Spinners in 3D from a mathematical
point of view
in the last video we introduced the
sigma matrices also called the poly
matrices we found that if we wrote a
vector using the sigma matrices as basis
vectors we ended up with a two by two
Matrix called a polyvector which is an
alternative way of writing a 3D vector
just as we can take certain two by two
matrices and write them as a column
times a row it's also possible to take
this 2x2 poly vector and write it as a
column times a row
this column and row are called poly
spinners
unlike traditional 3D vectors which
rotate with a single three by three
Matrix poly vectors are rotated with a
double-sided transformation using
special matrices called su2 matrices
if we Factor our polyvector into a pair
of poly Spinners then each spinner only
transforms with a single su2 Matrix this
explains why Spinners rotate half as
much as vectors do
before we start looking at Spinners
let's review basic 2x2 matrices
using array multiplication we can
multiply a column by a row to get a two
by two Matrix we just arrange them like
this and follow the standard rules of
array multiplication
1 times 3 equals three one times two
equals two negative four times three
equals negative 12 and negative 4 times
2 equals negative eight
now it's also possible to do this
process in reverse
given this 2x2 matrix we can ask how to
break it up into a column times a row
you can think of this as trying to solve
for these four variables a b c d
if you like you can pause and try to
figure it out but I'm going to give you
the answer
one solution is the column one four and
the Row 1 100.
however there are actually multiple
possible solutions to this problem
if we take our column row multiplication
we can put a number one in the middle
without changing anything
we can then break up this number one
into two times one-half multiplying the
column on the left by 2 gives us the
components 2 8 and multiplying the row
on the right by one half gives us one
half fifty
this gives us another solution which
also reproduces the same Matrix
in fact we can multiply the column by
any non-zero scaling Factor s and
multiply the row by one over s and still
get the same Matrix since the S and one
over s will cancel with each other
so there are an infinite number of
solutions to this problem of factoring a
matrix into a column and a row
if we were to write this column as a b
and the row as CD we could feel free to
multiply the column by 1 over a and
multiply the row by a to get another
valid solution
the resulting column has components one
B over a
while there are multiple possible
columns that can solve the factoring
problem the B over a ratio for all these
columns is the same
so when factoring a matrix we can get
multiple possible columns but there is
only one unique B over a ratio that
solves the factoring problem
so if you like you can convert this
factoring problem into a series of
equations and try solving for a b c and
d
since there are an infinite number of
solutions you'll have to make a decision
for what a should be before you solve
for the rest of the variables
now I should point out that not all two
by two matrices can be factored into a
column and a row for example this Matrix
here with the 400 changed to a 500
cannot be factored if you try to search
for ABCD numbers to solve this you'll
find that there are no Solutions
the reason this first Matrix can be
factored is because the columns are all
multiples of each other
here the First Column multiplied by 100
gives the second column
equivalently the rows are all multiples
of each other the first row multiplied
by four gives the second row
in the specific case of a two by two
Matrix these conditions are the same
thing as saying the determinant of the
Matrix is zero
with this other Matrix The Columns are
not multiples of each other and the
determinant is non-zero so it cannot be
factored into a column and a row
now if we bring back our poly Vector
let's try factoring this polyvector into
a row and a column in other words we
need to solve for these ABCD numbers
this gives us four equations
now let's keep a couple things in mind
while we solve this first remember that
there will be multiple Solutions because
we can always multiply the column by a
non-zero number s if we multiply the row
by one over s
also in order for solutions to exist the
determinant of this Matrix must be zero
recall from the last video that the
determinant of a polyvector is the
vector's negative squared length the
negative of x squared plus y squared
plus Z squared
when a vector has zero squared length we
call it an isotropic vector or sometimes
a null vector
keep in mind that the only way this
Vector can have zero squared length is
if all the components are zero or if at
least some of the components are complex
numbers
getting back to factoring the polyvector
since the squared length must be zero we
must have Z squared equals negative x
squared plus y squared
if we take the square root of both sides
we can pull the square root of negative
one out in front as I
now technically this square root could
have either a plus sign or a minus sign
in front and it would still satisfy our
original equation
but these basically correspond to the
two different cases of a positive Z
component and a negative Z component
so I'm only going to look at the
solutions with the plus sign in front of
the square root if you want the negative
Solutions you just need to change the
sign of the Z component in the poly
vector
if we look at our first component
equation Z equals a times C it would be
useful if we could take our equation for
Z over here and Factor the right hand
side into two parts that way we can set
one of them to a and set the other one
to C
to do this we're going to treat the
expression under the square root sign as
a difference of squares
it's true that this looks like a sum of
squares but we can turn a sum of squares
into a difference of squares by changing
the sign and including a factor of
negative one here and negative one is
really I squared and if we bring the I
inside the same square as y we now have
a difference of squares
remember we can always factor a
difference of squares into two terms the
left term involving the first variable
minus the second variable and the right
term involving the first variable plus
the second variable
and for reasons of following convention
I'm going to move the eye over here
so we've successfully written Zed as a
product of two terms and we can set
these equal to a and C
using our Solutions 4 A and C we can
solve for b and d b ends up being equal
to negative C and D ends up being equal
to a
so we've successfully factored our poly
Vector into a column and a row and I'm
going to call these two component
objects poly spinners
and I'm going to rewrite R A and B
components as the Greek letters PSI 1
and PSI 2 with upper indices
so just keep in mind that these are
column indices and not exponents they're
just labels that indicate where the
component belongs in the left column
I'm also going to mention that many
sources include factors of 1 over the
square root of two in these components
and include a factor of two in front of
the array multiplication to compensate
for them
but I don't plan on doing that so this
is the solution we'll be using
so we've discovered a solution to the
problem of factoring a polyvector into a
column and a row the components PSI 1
and PSI 2 are given in terms of X and Y
by these formulas
we can also solve for x y and z in terms
of PSI 1 and PSI 2.
now of course there are multiple
solutions for these PSI components
we can always multiply the column
Spinner by a complex number with
magnitude a and phase Theta if we divide
the row Spinner by the same complex
number
for example we could always multiply the
column Spinner by one over PSI 1 giving
us the components one and the ratio PSI
2 over x i 1.
so while there are multiple possible
column Spinners that solve this
factoring problem for a given poly
Vector the ratio PSI 2 over PSI 1 will
be the same for all the solutions
this ratio is a single complex number in
the case of spinners with a ratio where
the denominator is zero these are
related to the point at Infinity a
concept from projective geometry I
covered in video 5.
this relates back to the two physical
applications of spinners we discussed in
videos two through five the polarization
of light waves and Quantum spin States
LightWave polarizations can be described
by a pair of complex numbers one for the
horizontal polarization and one for the
vertical polarization
the complex numbers tell us the
amplitude and phase of each polarization
overall scaling of the wave does not
change the polarization and overall
phase factors just shifts the wave along
the axis of travel without changing the
polarization so LightWave polarizations
are unchanged by overall multiplication
by complex numbers
we also learned Quantum spin states in
the stern gerlock experiment are
described by a pair of complex numbers
one for the spin up probability
amplitude and one for the spin down
probability amplitude
the probability of state A collapsing
onto State B is given by born's rule
if we multiply State a by a complex
number the normalization in the
denominator eliminates the scale factor
and the absolute value eliminates the
phase Factor giving us the same
probability result we originally had
so Quantum states are unchanged by
overall multiplication by complex
numbers
so both light wave polarizations and
Quantum spin states are described by a
pair of complex numbers whose states are
unaffected by overall complex number
multiplication
in other words it is only the ratio of
their components that matters
this is similar to the poly Spinners
we've discovered in this video where a
given Vector produces a unique ratio of
poly spinner components
in mathematical terms when several
Spinners have the same component ratio
we do consider them to be different
Spinners but they are all associated
with the same Vector so they can be
grouped together in a kind of family
recall from the last video that
polyvectors rotate with double-sided su2
transformations
once we factor a polyvector into a pair
of poly Spinners we see that each poly
spinner rotates with a single su2 Matrix
the column spinner rotates with an su2
Matrix multiplied from the left
and the row spinner rotates with the
same su2 Matrix but hermitian conjugated
and multiplied from the right
we also saw that Spinners describing
LightWave polarizations and Quantum spin
States rotated with su2 matrices on the
poincare sphere and block sphere
the reason su2 matrices are able to
rotate a spinner PSI is that the
Spinners squared magnitude is given by
the hermitian conjugate of PSI times PSI
when we transform PSI using a unitary
Matrix U we can flip these around and
cancel U dagger and U to the identity
Matrix Since U is unitary and this gives
us the same squared magnitude for the
spinner
so unitary matrices rotate Spinners
around without changing their length
now we've learned how to factor a
polyvector into a pair of poly Spinners
only if the vector's squared length is
zero
this is called an isotropic vector or
null vector and either all the XYZ
components must be zero or at least some
of the XYZ components must be complex
but what if the vector's components are
all real and non-zero then it's
impossible for the squared length to be
zero
we can ask ourselves if it's still
possible to factor this polyvector into
spinners
it turns out that we can Factor it into
Spinners if we use a trick
let's go back to this Matrix with
components 1 100 4 500 this matrix's
determinant is non-zero and so we can't
Factor it directly into a column and a
row
however we can write it as a sum of four
matrices one for each of the four
components where all the other
components are zero
then we can pull the numbers out in
front as scaling factors so that the
matrices are made up of only ones and
zeros
now all of these four matrices now have
determinants of zero so they can be
factored into a column and a row
for example this Matrix can be factored
into the column 1 0 and the row one zero
we can do something similar for the
other matrices
so we've successfully decomposed this
Matrix into a sum of column row products
even though we can't Factor it directly
into a single column and a single row we
can still express it as a sum of column
row products
the same thing applies to poly vectors
when a poly vector's determinant is
non-zero we can't Factor it directly
into a column spinner row spinner
product
but we can break it apart and write it
as a sum of column row products with
different scaling factors in front
and these columns and rows are all poly
spinners
when we rotate the vector using a
double-sided su-2 transformation the
column Spinners will all transform with
an su2 Matrix on the left
and all the row Spinners will transform
with a hermitian conjugated su2 Matrix
on the right
so to summarize the properties of poly
Spinners they are pairs of complex
numbers that we get when we factor a 3D
polyvector into a column and a row
there are multiple solutions to this
factoring problem but there is a unique
ratio of spinner components that solves
the problem for a given vector
this factoring can only be done directly
if the vector has zero squared length
which means it's an isotropic Vector
also called a null vector
for non-isotropic vectors we can instead
break the poly Vector up into several
matrices with zero determinants and
Factor each one into a column spinner
and a row spinner
finally while polyvectors rotate with a
pair of su2 matrices one on each side
column Spinners and row Spinners each
rotate with a single su2 Matrix
as an exercise you can try calculating
the polyvector XYZ components for these
poly Spinners and check if they make
sense in relation to each other